Taha Ahmed

Certified HR Professional / Licensed NLP Practitioner

Contact Details: 0092 333 2265877 – 0092 213 6804165 Email Address: tahaahmed161@gmail.com Resident of: Karachi - Pakistan



Professional Summary:

I've spent up to 10 years of experience exactly in HR and fulfilling my responsibilities and polished my skills in almost every area of Human Resources that includes Talent Management, Organizational Development, Performance Management, Learning & Development and Compensation & Benefits. I have a wide experience in working with different sectors and enhance my skills to achieve the excellence.

Achievements:

- ✓ Re-certification of ISO 9001, 14001 & 22000
- ✓ Employee Satisfaction Survey. (Employee Empowerment)
- ✓ Developed & implemented grading & salary structure.
- ✓ Work Load Analysis & organizational restructuring.
- ✓ HR Policies Diagnosis & reengineering.

- / Implementation of ERP in organization
- ✓ Better Performance Appraisal Systems.
- ✓ Develop & implement competency model.
- ✓ Conduct Job Analysis & Job Evaluation.

Professional Experience:

Organization: Aga Khan Education Service, Pakistan (NGO / Education Sector)

Department: Human Resources | Regional Manager HR | From March 2019 to November 2019

Reporting To: Head of Human Resources

- > Job Responsibilities
- Responsible for HR operations in AKES,P's Southern Region units.
- Reporting of data analytics through regular maintenance of key HR metrics.
- Liaison with Central HR team for OD interventions.
- Review, suggest, implement and evaluate policies and procedures.
- Develop manpower plans and assist in the budgets for the company.
- Builds applicant sources by researching and contacting universities, recruiters, media, and internet sites.
- Evaluates applicants by discussing job requirements and applicant qualifications with managers;
- Ensuring all recruitments / transfers / promotions / regularizations / salary revisions, are within budget & aligned with HR policy.
- Manage & implement employee on-boarding activities.
- Implement Performance Management Review System effectively for bonus and increment distribution.
- Ensure compliance of performance appraisals as per policy and procedures.
- Responsible to manage over all HR budgeting activities of South region.
- Ensure timely & accurate processing of monthly payroll (including attendance, overtime, allowances, income tax deduction, and other deductions) in coordination with regional schools and Central Office.
- Ensure all the benefits (leaves, EOBI, SESSI, freeship, provident fund, health & life insurance, over time etc.) are administrated.
- Identifying and assessing future and current training needs.
- Manage and resolve employee relations issues.
- Maintaining appropriate procedures for handling disciplinary issues and disputes in liaison with legal department.
- Liaison with EOBI & SESSI.
- Handle all internal and external HR related audit queries for the South Region.
- Conduct Training Need Analysis.
- Provide coaching & training to staff.
- Monitoring and reviewing the development programs of teachers.
- Member of Procurement committee.

Organization: Habib Oil Mills, Karachi - Pakistan (FMCG / Edible Oil)

Habib Oil Mills, Habib Quality Foods, Habib First Water, Millennium IT Solutions

Department: Human Resources | Deputy Manager HR (Leading HR Function) | From Aug 2014 to Dec 2018

Reporting To: General Manager Human Resources

> Job Responsibilities

Organizational Development & Performance Management:

- Assist department heads in making an appropriate departmental structure.
- Align business objectives with respective business units.
- Develop, implement and evaluate policies and procedures.
- Prepare a process / frame work for the succession planning.
- Prepare occupational classifications, J.D. and salary scales.
- Provide recommendations to ensure HR processes and procedures are lean and understood by colleagues across the company.
- Responsible for HR Audit.
- Manage & improve and implement HR Information System.
- Ensure that all documentation related to ISO certification is up to date and complete.
- Establish Performance management system that increases the system efficiency and effectiveness.
- Identifying development needs through job analysis, appraisal schemes and regular consultation with managers.
- Develop competencies of all positions available in company.
- Implement competency model to improve performance appraisals, hiring employees etc.
- Lead on data analytic and reporting through regular reporting of key HR metrics.

Compensation, Benefits & Payroll:

- Critically review and analyze current payroll and benefits in order to recommend and implement changes leading to best-practice.
- Manage Payroll process and ensure its timely completion and resolve payroll discrepancies.
- Maintain systems to process payroll (e.g. salaries, benefits, income tax, deductions, variable payments etc.)
- Manage, improve and implement HR Information System for effective process of payroll.
- Forecast budget for salary increases.
- Ensure and oversee effective implementation of various variable pay and sales commission schemes across the organization.
- Manager 3rd party payroll.
- Administering the organization's benefits programs (e.g., insurance policies, retirements, EOBI, ESSI etc.)
- Ensure compliance of performance appraisals as per policy and procedures.
- Maintain and implement pay for performance system to process bonus and annual increments.
- Responsible to manage over all HR budgeting activities.
- Monitor KPIs like overtime rates, health claim ratios, and payroll cycle time.

Talent Management:

- Develop manpower plans and assist in the budgets for the company.
- Establish and manage the talent acquisition function by making sustainable talent acquisition and hiring strategies.
- Prepare the analysis on current and future risk attach to the company human resources requirement.
- Design & implementation of employer branding strategies with marketing team.
- Manage and monitor Talent KPIs that includes Hiring cost, Time to fill, Time to get qualified candidates etc.
- Monitor Turnover rates that include first year turnover, total turnover, voluntary turnover, involuntary turnover.
- Builds applicant sources by researching and contacting universities, recruiters, media, and internet sites.
- Evaluates applicants by discussing job requirements and applicant qualifications with managers;
- Interviewing applicants on consistent set of qualifications.
- Conduct effective employee orientation program.
- Manage & implement employee on-boarding activities.

Learning & Development:

- Conduct Training Need Analysis (TNA).
- Identifying and assessing future and current training needs.
- Develop departmental staff by providing coaching & training.
- Monitoring and reviewing the progress of trainees through questionnaires and discussions with managers.
- Helping line managers and trainers solve specific training problems, either on a one-to-one basis or in groups.
- Supervise technical & soft skills training for staff both in-house and off-shore.
- Maintain awareness and knowledge of contemporary HR practices and provide suitable interpretation to management and staff.
- Conduct and monitor Employee Engagement activities, survey and its action plan.
- Implement & supervise employee engagement activities.
- Monitor ROI of training and training effectiveness index & efficiency.

Employee & Industrial Relations:

- Manage and resolve employee relations issues.
- Ensure company compliance with federal and state laws, including reporting requirements.
- Handle disciplinary issues as per the state laws in liaison with company's lawyer.
- Maintaining appropriate procedures for handling disciplinary, grievances, harassment and discrimination issues and disputes.
- Liaison with EOBI & SESSI.
- Ensure health & safety compliance of employees in accordance with state laws and other compliance bodies.

Organization: Sharp Image Animations, Karachi – Pakistan (Entertainment / IT Solutions)

Department: Human Resources | Deputy Manager HR | January 2013 to March 2014

Reporting To: CEO/COO

> Job Responsibilities

• Talent Acquisition

• Performance Management

• Compensation, Benefits & Payroll

Organizational Development

Learning & Development

General Operations

Organization: Rehmpack (Pvt.) Ltd., Karachi – Pakistan (Packaging Sector)

Department: Human Resources | Assistant Manager HR | February 2012 to December 2012

Reporting To: Managing Director

> Job Responsibilities

Talent Acquisition

• Performance Management

• Compensation, Benefits & Payroll

Organizational Development

• Learning & Development

General Operations

Organization: Abudawood Trading Co., Karachi – Pakistan (Distribution Sector)

Department: Human Resources | H.R. Specialist | February 2010 to September 2011

Reporting To: Manager HR

> Job Responsibilities

• Talent Acquisition

• Performance Management

Organizational Development

• Compensation, Benefits & Payroll

Organization: Meezan Bank Ltd., Karachi – Pakistan (Financial Sector)

Department: Human Resources | HR Officer | From March 2006 to September 2007

Professional Qualification:

Education	Year	Institution
PGD HR	2018	Institute of Business Management (IoBM).
MBA	2010	Muhammad Ali Jinnah University, Karachi

International Certificates & Awards:

- People Analytics & Evidence Based Management from Mannheim Business School Germany / SAP
- Instructional System Design for Trainers **from** Alison (Social Education Enterprise Ireland).
- Licensed NLP Practitioner **from** American Board of Neuro Linguistic Programming.
- Certified Human Resources Professional (CHRP)TM
 from GAQM, UK

Other Certificates & Awards:

- Diploma in Labour Law & Industrial Relations from Skill Development Council.
- ISO 14001: 2004 standard & ISO 22000: 2013 standard from SGS.
- Pakistan Standards for Halal Food Management System (PS:3733-2016) from IFANCA.

References: Furnished upon Request